Register to the Hans L. Bilger Papers
Yale University Music Library
Hans L. Bilger Papers
1918-1939
MSS 95
Yale University Music Library
0.5
(1 box)
Music by the American composer Hans L. Bilger (1896-1968)
Bilger, Hans L., 1896-1968
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Hans L. Bilger Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University by Bilger's niece, Linda Murray Berzok, in 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Biographical / Historical
The American composer Hans L. Bilger (1896-1968) received the B.M. degree from the Yale School of Music in 1920. He was active in Connecticut in the 1930s. Further biographical information is not available.
Scope and Contents
The Hans L. Bilger Papers consist chiefly of Bilger's compositions, both published and in manuscript. They also include music by other composers, song lyrics, two concert programs, and drawings of historical musical instruments.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Music. II. Miscellaneous.
Bilger, Hans L., 1896-1968
- Music, Series I
  - Music by Hans L. Bilger, Sub-Series I.A
    - Instrumental Music, Sub-Series I.A.1
      - [Fugue, organ, C minor] Fugue in C minor: organ / H. L. Bilger., 8 ms. p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        General
        Holograph in ink.
      - [Fugue, organ, C minor] Fugue in C minor for organ / H. L. Bilger., 10 p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - [Fugue, piano, C minor] Fugue for piano in 3 voices / H. L. Bilger., 4 ms. p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        On t.p: Yale University, June 1918.
      - [Overture, C minor] Overture in C minor / H. L. Bilger., 1 ms. score (51 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Holograph in ink, annotations in colored pencil.
      - [Overture, C minor] Symphonic overture in C minor / H. L. Bilger., 1 ms. score (47 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Holograph in pencil.
        At end: Yale Univ. 1920
      - [Overture, C minor] Overture in C minor / H. L. Bilger., 24 ms. parts (71 p. total); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Ms., in part holograph in ink.
      - [Overture, C minor; arr.] Overture - C minor / H. L. Bilger., 9 ms. p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Arr. for piano solo.
      - [Overture, C minor; arr.] Overture in C minor / H. L. Bilger. – 1920., 13 p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Holograph in pencil and ink.
        Arr. for piano, with annotations and additions for organ.
      - [Scarecrow dance] Intro - scare-crow dance., 1 ms. score (2 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Cues for piano and organ.
      - [Sonata, violin, piano, G minor] Sonata in G minor: violin & piano / H. L. Bilger. – September, 1919., 1 score (12 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Score only, lacks separate violin part.
      - The sun worshippers: Zuni Indian melody., 2 ms. p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
        For piano solo.
      - Sunday morning / music by H. L. Bilger. – 1927., 8 p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Identified on typescript list of works as Sunday Morning at Dusseldorf.
      - [Variations, piano, G major] Theme with variations for piano / H. L. Bilger., 4 p. of ms. music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
        At top: Free Composition, Feb. 5, 1919.
      - Wooden shoe dance / H. L. Bilger., 3 p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Songs, Sub-Series I.A.2
      - All in all / words by Bliss Carmen; music by H. L. Bilger. – Philadelphia: Theodore Presser, c1930., 1 score (5 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
        For voice and piano.
      - April / lyric by Theodosia Garrison; music by H. L. Bilger. – New York: E. Morris Music Pub., c1925. (Box 1, Folder 15)
        1 score (3 p.); 31 cm.
      - Clouds / lyric by Sydney Stone Field; music by Hans L. Bilger. – New York: Edward Morris Music Pub., c1929., 1 score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - I married a wife / [lyric by] Warren Gilbert; [music by] H. L. Bilger. – 1928., 1 ms. score (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
        For voice and piano, in E-flat.
      - If I were not a little girl / lyric by Violet Alleyn Storey; music by H. L. Bilger. – New York: Edward Morris Music Pub., c1927., 1 score (3 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Little boy of mine / poem by Alice P. Whiteside; music by Hans L. Bilger. – New York: Edward Morris Music Pub., c1929., 1 score (5 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - [Lonely things], 1 ms. score (2 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 20)
        For voice and piano, in F minor.
      - Lonely things: song / [lyric by] Helen Magaret; [music by] H. L. Bilger., 1 ms. score (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 21)
        At end: Poem published in Harper's Magazine.
      - The Lord of glory / words and music by H. L. Bilger. – Philadelphia: Theodore Presser, c1932., 1 score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Mother-mine / [lyric by] Jean Mertinett; [music by] H. L. Bilger. – c1924., 1 ms. score (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
        For voice and piano, in B-flat.
        At top: To Mebane Hunt.
        Publisher information written onto bottom.
      - Mother-mine / lyric by Jean Martinett; music by H. L. Bilger. – New York: Edward Morris Music Pub., c1924., 1 score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
        For voice and piano, in D.
      - My garden / poem anonymous; music by H. L. Bilger. – London: Arthur H. Stockwell, c1930., 1 score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - The path of yesterday / poem by Grantland Rice; music by H. L. Bilger. – New York: Edward Morris Music Pub., c1928., 1 score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - A poor unfortunate / lyric by F. L. Stanton; music by H. L. Bilger., 1 ms. score (6 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 25)
        At end: Roanoke, Va., December 1926.
        At end: Printed in The Atlanta Constitution.
      - [Song the grass sings] Encore song: A song the grass sings / lyric by Charles G. Blanden; music by H. L. Bilger. – c1931., 1 score (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 26)
        For voice and piano, in F.
        At end: Feb, 1929, Roanoke, Va.
      - A song the grass sings / poem by Charles G. Blanden; music by H. L. Bilger. – Boston: Oliver Ditson, c1932., 1 score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - When I was one and twenty / words by A. E. Housman; music by H. L. Bilger. – Philadelphia: Theodore Presser, c1927., 1 score (5 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Music by Other Composers, Sub-Series I.B
    - [Keyboard music. Selections] Pavana: the Earle of Salisbury [etc.] / William Byrde., Byrd, William, 1542 or 3-1623; 2 ms. p. of music; 27 x 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Copyist's ms. in ink.
      Contents: Pavana: The Earle of Salisbury – The Garman Whistle – Andantino and Coda of Sellengers Round (contains variations)
    - Sunny Sue / Walter Donaldson; arr. by B., Donaldson, Walter, 1893-1947; 1 ms. score (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 29)
      At end: New York City, Dec. 1921.
    - Red Godwin's wooing: dramatic ballad for male voices and solo voice / by William E. Haesche., Haesche, William E. (William Edwin), 1867-1929; 1 ms. score (43 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Possibly holograph, in pencil, ink, and colored ink.
- Miscellaneous, Series II
  - Typescript poems for use as lyrics., 10 p. total. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Scope and Contents
    Cherry-Ripe / Anon. Clouds / Sydney Stone. Field Empty Praise / Violet Alleyn Storey. If I Were Not a Little Girl / Violet Alleyn Storey (on verso: Rock Me to Sleep in Georgia Again / Cecil B. Sledge). Little Boy of Mine / Alice P. Whiteside. An Old Fashioned Garden / Author unknown (on verso: Rock Me to Sleep in Georgia Again / Cecil B. Sledge). When I Was One and Twenty / A. E. Housman.
  - Programs (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Virginia College, Roanoke, Virginia, Saturday, December 14, 1929. Bridgeport Federal Symphony Orchestra, Wednesday, May 24 [probably 1939].
  - Typescript list of compositions, with annotations (1 p.) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Drawings of historical musical instruments and chant, hand-colored., 15 p. total; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Copied from pictures in magazines such as Harpers New Monthly Magazine and The Musician (Boston)